this is majaya
107 so I have heard at one time the
Buddha was staying near Savi in the
Eastern Monastery the stilt long House
of migara's mother then the Brahman
molana the accountant went up to the
Buddha and exchanged pleasantries with
him when the amicable and cordial talk
was over he sat down to one side and
said to the Buddha Master Goa in this
stilt long house we can see sequential
progress down to the last step of the
staircase among the brahin we can see
sequential progress in learning the
chance among among archers we can see
sequential progress in archery Among Us
accountants who earn a living by
accounting we can see sequential
progress in calculation for when we get
an apprentice we first make them count 1
1 2 tws 33s four fours 55s so on to 10 T
we even make them count up to 100 it is
possible to sim is it possible to
similarly describe a sequential training
sequential progress and sequential
practice in this teaching and discipline
it is possible Brahman suppose a deaf
horse trainer were to obtain a fine
thorough bread first first of all he'd
make it get used to wearing the bit in
the same way when the realized one gets
a person for for training they first
guide them like this come biku live
fulfilling virtue and the training rules
live restrained by the code of conduct
endowed with proper behavior and a
suitable environment seeing danger in
the slightest fault train in the
training rules y so we can go one by one
so the first thing to note there is as
it's saying sequential progress it's uh
so
it's the the point is the main reason
why the training has to go in the order
that described not only there but
probably dozens of times throughout the
sutas is
because the more subtle aspect of the
training which people unfortunately like
to start with a lot of the time such as
somi mindfulness all these things um the
defilements and and issues that these
things are supposed to address will not
have even be been revealed unless you're
keeping those first um you've
solidified your practice on those more
uh basic levels so like that's why
actually if you if you uh kind of tell a
person and talk to talk to a person just
about sensor strength not even the other
stuff and you tell them
uh okay practice sensor trange somebody
who hasn't practiced virtue at
all the natural idea would be like oh so
I must not see anything I must you know
lock myself into a
cave um not see people not eat not smell
and then you know they hear about the
whole abandonment of sensuality and they
literally think it's about you know not
avoiding the things that come through
your senses
uh and that's that's one very coar
example of how uh you wouldn't really be
able to see what the work is in relation
to these more subtle things unless you
have developed the ones that come first
so that's why through throughout the
whole suta um the Buddha basically goes
on and says when abiku is uh established
in virtue then I tell him do this when a
virtue abiku is establishing sense
restraint then I I tell him to do this
so um in the same way like you wouldn't
have the the
accountant uh counting tens when he
hasn't learned how to count ones it just
doesn't make sense or you wouldn't be
building the last step of the staircase
when you haven't built the first one um
so that's why it's a gradual training
kind of uh carries the implication that
it's slow but that's not necessarily
what it means anba the meaning in P is
sequential so like in some sutas you
know it would describe that people would
gain arship within two weeks stuff like
that so not necessarily slow it's just
that it has to go in that sequence it it
builds yeah in layers it builds upon
itself like the the the the
uh um stuff that you have done in the
previous steps is not that you abandon
it you actually um refine it so the the
the the principle of virtue not acting
out of un wholesome state by body and
speech actually carries on all the way
to the very
end so would it be kind of um an apt
so would it be kind of um an apt
comparison to say like if somebody's
trying to learn how to say computer
program first step is you need a
computer that's not like something you
just do and then set aside it's like no
like the entire rest of that learning
process is through having a computer you
need one to yeah you could say like
first you yeah so within knowing how to
use a computer you'll be able to learn
how to program right it's not like step
one you learn this line of code and then
step two you learn this line of code you
could have done it in a different order
it's like no step one is absolutely
essential for everything that follows
yeah yeah so that's that's the the basic
um principle behind it it's not that you
know usually it would be taken as a
almost abstract or or um nebulous
ambiguous connection between virtue and
and everything else like they would
think okay like virtue calms your mind
down or something partially that's true
but more primordially it's like you
don't even know what you're looking for
with these other things unless you have
developed cuz virtue in in and of itself
it's going to start revealing these
Tendencies of the mind it's going to
start revealing
you know when I don't do these things
this is how my mind behaves and then you
realize oh so you begin to recognize
what actually the training is before
that you might have thought oh it's just
uh I need to stop like I said um become
unaware of things or or stop perceiving
them but no you these things are already
showing you that it's not the problem is
not in the things the problem is how the
mind reacts when you don't go towards
them or when when they're Pleasant or
when you don't allow yourself to to run
away from them when they're unpleasant
so it reveals what uh the problem is
basically just before reading on there's
um it's
um kind of seeing danger in the
slightest fault that's not an
insignificant yeah yeah thing like this
isn't just like okay I'm at a monastery I've
just like okay I'm at a monastery I've
like decided I'm going to keep the eight
precepts for you know the duration of my
stay all right Next Step like it's
like you really have to kind
of like take it on and seriously at that
um I'm curious if you have more to kind
of say about just like that slightest
fault yeah so it's it's slightest fault
would mean that's another thing usually we
mean that's another thing usually we
hear about the precepts and we assume
it's just okay so you you're almost like
looking for when it where it stops so
that you can keep on at least a little
bit of of uh following your desires but
actually should go the opposite
direction it should be like um how far
can I actually push it without you know
going into self modification or whatever
so um yeah so you might not be let
say um
um
lying but are you still trying to
um well not acknowledging things that
you know you should acknowledge like
when you when you um do something wrong
and and you like nobody asked you nobody
has has uh you're not explicitly telling
a lie but you're kind of covering it up
so that other people don't find out um
you know yes like oh and and celibacy
which is one of the most important ones
you would see for example this is where
the Buddha talked about the flaws of
celibacy I think was the name and he
would say oh there there atics and
brahans who would think that just
because they refrain from sexual
intercourse they're celibate but then it
would say like oh but they still allow
themselves to be massaged by women and
then they yeah yeah then then they and then
they yeah yeah then then they and then
some of them wouldn't go that far but
then they still um you know hear them
laughing and and and uh you know Delight
in in that um just in that sense object
and then uh and then it goes all the way
to the point where uh some of them don't
do had nothing to do with it in this
life but they're still hoping that as a
result of this practice they will be
reborn heaven where they'll be able to
enjoy suchal pleasures and uh he would
say all of that is is a is a fault of
the um of the celibate life brah mataria
and um similarly there is majima 16
where it would say whoever is not um
whoever still has passion for sensual
Pleasures um whoever cult definitely whoever
um whoever cult definitely whoever
cultivates that passion
and uh even whoever is wishing for
Heavenly rewards out of their practice
he says um it's impossible that they
would come to maturity and development
in in the dhama and discipline
so yeah you certainly have to stop
nurturing it that's the main that's the
main um main thing obviously you still
you won't be able to abandon overnight
but if you're like nurturing it by for
example not being s ofate and then at
the same time
trying to cultivate these other things
that are based on this passion like what
is niana the relinquishment of all
Appropriations the the sensation of
craving dispassion uh and then at the same time
dispassion uh and then at the same time
you're like building up Acquisitions and
building up passions well that's that's
like trying to have hot and cold water
at the same time you can't if you want
to merge off the highway you got to slow
down a little bit yeah
so um when said biku is virtuous the
realized one guides him further come
biku guard your sense doors when you see
a sight with the eyes don't grasp it
signs and features of it on account of
which due to abiding with the eye
faculty unrestrained bad detrimental
phenomena of longing and upset would
flow in on you practice to restrain that
guard the eye faculty and bring about
Restraint of the eye faculty so on
hearing a sound um when you taste when
you touch um when you smell Miss um when
you cognize a phenomenon with your mind
don't grasp its signs and features of it
on account of which due to abiding with
the mental faculty unrestrained bad's
detrimental phenomena of longing and
upset would flow in on you practice to
restrain that guard the mental faculty
and bring about bring about the
Restraint of the mental
faculty so just a basic question would
you be able to not grasp the signs and
features of of these sense objects when
you already acted out of them like can
you say I am not grasping the signs and
features that arous lust but I am having
sexual intercourse right well you might be able
intercourse right well you might be able
to kind of Identify some signs and
features that you're not actively giving
into but yeah you're you're overlooking
the the actual issue yeah yeah like you
you can focus on very specific things
that maybe you no longer attend to as
much but the the bulk of it is still
Auto it's actually automatically there
as soon as because grasping the signs
and features is a mental thing so
actions by body and speech is like way
down the line so uh sensor straint is
already basically once you have
restrained your body and speech which by
the way the the precepts um like the
first part that talks
about uh basically The Virtue doesn't
just refer to bodily actions it also
refers to verbal restraint like you know
as the as a SS would say it's not just
that you don't um yourself it but you
also even refrain from talking about
sensual um subjects so uh sensor
restraint once it it progresses onto
sens restraint is because basically that
verbal that's where the extent of the
verbal and bodily domain the precepts
and the seeing the danger in the sight
is fault and then when it comes to the
mind um it begins with sensor change and
actually I think there's there yeah
there's the suta and nikaya where the
Buddha is describing the three
Aggregates like the aggregate of virtue
aggregate of samadi and aggregate of of
wisdom and then the aggregate of samadi
begins with sensor strength so that's
already taking you in that direction
that's already a further step um in in
the direction of now more the
mind and then um yeah so that would
be um yeah so we have the whole essay on
the uh restraining the senses that I
wrote uh but yeah it's just um as I said
before if you haven't uh restrained your
actions first that principle these signs
and features which is kind of like that
sound abstract to people you wouldn't be
able to know uh what that even means
it's it's when you have been restraining
your actions see over time of doing that
not just like one evening or something
uh you will begin to realize oh
actually yes so I'm not acting anymore
but there's still something that I'm
doing mentally that's leading me to have
these pressure and and and um
inclination for my mind to want to do
these things even though I'm sure I'm
not going to do them because I'm
establishing the precepts there's still
something I'm doing there with my mind
that leads me to as it says being these
states flowing
in um you get kind
of like as close to doing it as you can
without actually like you know you're
not going to actually go buy cigarettes
but you're still going to go to the gas
station just to look at them almost yeah
something like that yeah so it's it's a
um see and again if you if you didn't
have that boundary that I'm definitely
not going to do this it's just
impossible cuz from the very start like
that analogy that you gave from the very
start that the moment that you left your
home like and you decided I am going to
go there and buy cigarettes the signs
and features are already grasped so that
you can get to the gas station and I
don't know pretend that the cigarettes
don't exist or something and then or or
or do do some sort of mental gymnastics
around it but everything is within
already you having grasped the signs and
features by not having restrained the
the actions beforehand and and it's not
just um
like uh the the signs and features would
include even um future things that's
where for example um let's say you you
on a present
basis uh one good example is these uh
10day meditation Retreats that that
people often do you during that time you
you do have
a you have made a determination that you
will not be um breaking the precepts or
whatever but in the future you still
have a sense of like I you know
everybody knows like once I leave once I
leave here I will continue to do those
things and that is grasping the signs
and features already um cuz it it
pertains both to the past and to the
Future it's not just right now so um
that's why you cannot as we've said
before you cannot uh abandon things
temporarily even when you um like when
you fully withdraw yourself from
sensuality in the first J it is a
permanent abandonment that doesn't last
forever but like within that time it is
permanent so to say that sounds like a
paradox but it's like what it means is
you factually at that moment don't have
any inclination even for the future to
do it so it's not like that you have
planned beforehand oh only for the next
two hours and that's why it's actually
the Su to say um it's not up to a person
to decide I will enter the first Jana
nor is it for them up to them to decide
when I will leave the first J and people
would think oh that's um that's like a
uh the state with your eyes closed and
stuff that that you know you're just
locked in there and you can't come out
of it no what it means is uh you won't
be able to Delight you won't be able to
decide when the the sensal desire will
come back like when the hindrances will
come back even if you're living out
there in the world and doing stuff the
the state will remain for as long as uh
depending on the strength of of the
establishment so um that in that sense
it's like
indefinitely stretch towards the
future just to come back a little bit on
the analogy you made like with the
someone that goes to the shop to buy
like a cigarette like it's literally
like impossible for him to see like this
inclination that he have even though
like he's not with the cigarette yet but
he's wanting to have them if he's
already in the car smoking a cigarette
you know what I mean like if he doesn't
abandon like this kind of
gross I mean you want to Abundant
cigarettes obviously you have to put
down the cigarettes stop like smoking it
in order to see his inclination so it's
the same with the virtue and the preet
like if we don't abandon like the Go
stuff first it's literally impossible to
see like the inclination of and and not
just like particularly as I said
abandoning the actions like abandon
planning to do it cuz that's how then
okay you abandon planning to do it and
then you see even then you have like
um that's where the the how to put it
it's like like an
like like an
animal that uh was passing through a
gate unhindered every time and now you
put the gate there and now you start
hearing the animal knocking against the
gate so you know exactly where was the
point where it was crossing but before
like you have no idea where it is that
it's it's passing through so it's like a
fence you have to fence it off and then
you'll be able to find out like the
tracks okay so this is where it used to
come in through but before that it's
like you might be
guarding as much as you want like you
have three
fences then you're standing you're
standing in the the the middle there
like with guns or whatever it doesn't
matter like it there is space for
whoever wants to come in to go in and
that's when people would be for example
you haven't gotone into that part yet
but doing the mindfulness and and the
recollection and awareness that it would
say like um when you're bending your arm
uh walking sitting speaking you do so
with mindfulness and that would be like
yeah so guarding the Gateway super you
know judiciously forgetting that actually the
judiciously forgetting that actually the
whole property there's still plenty of
room for anybody
Without You noticing yeah Step One is
like fening fening it off yeah yeah but
people often take it to be like all
right step one I have to be like yeah
you know every time I move a little bit
you know I got to got to be paying
attention and that's why see you would
be
misconceiving um what that even
means even though you're reading it and
sort of makes sense but you're
misconceiving what it actually means
just because you haven't developed those
prerequisites
so when the biku has his sense sense
doors guarded the realized one guides
him further come biku be moderate in
eating eat reflecting through the origin
not for fun Indulgence adornment or
decoration but only to sustain this body
to avoid harm and to support the
renunciate life in this way I shall to
put an end to Old discomfort and not
give rise to new discomfort and I will
live blamelessly and at
ease yeah so that's um that's a more
specific way in which you would be
grasping the signs and features like
um with food you have no say in uh the
fact that food will be pleasant like you
can decide to only eat like the like The
Janes were doing like you know
sometimes I think even eating dirt and
and leaves and stuff and sure in the
beginning it's going to be disgusting
but eventually at some point you get
used to it and it's like the stuff that
um just just the plain fact of eating is
going to carry pleasure with it so then
uh that's actually quite a quite um
integral um it it would very acutely show you the
um it it would very acutely show you the
principle of of how to not have passion
even though Pleasant feeling is
there uh
so instead of like you know starting
again with meditation where you wouldn't
really see how is it that you can have
um feelings arising on their own without
you delighting in
them this would actually teach you that
before you get to that point uh it would
you would realize yeah I have no say in
the fact that sometimes food will be
pleasant but then you you recognize I I
actually do have a choice in whether I'm
eating that food as it says there for
fun for beautification for pleasure uh
and um like most often even you would be
um like most often even you would be
eating past the point where you're
actually satisfying the hunger you would
be eating like as it says they're
creating new discomfort like overeating
just because your motivation for eating
was wrong it was uh to get as much of
this pleasure as you want and obviously
then you will
overshoot uh beyond the the the point of
practical point of keeping yourself
alive so but again like you wouldn't
so but again like you wouldn't
um that's another one actually when when
uh in Retreats and stuff you would see
people like eating super slowly and you
know trying to be extra mindful of every
single morsel and feeling it see that's
already misconceiving uh it doesn't talk
about that it says be clear about your
motivation that it's not for fun not for
beautification not for pleasure and that
would only be be apparent like those
subtle motivations through sensory
strength cuz it's through grasping the
wrong signs and features that are there
in relation to the
food that uh you would be doing it out
of those wrong reasons so uh it's it's
the same thing the signs and features of
agreeability will be there but because
you learned the sense rest straint
beforehand now you'll be able to apply
it even on that level so that's
interesting because the sense restraint
you know it does talk about kind of
tongue faculty um so that
like and also if you're following the
eight precepts their eating is kind of
implicit in every other step that came
before this one so there's kind of like
a very yeah cuz there there can still be
a refinement to it like yeah if you're
keeping a precept for example you're not
eating you would maybe not necessarily
eat uh after um one meal a day or whatever
uh after um one meal a day or whatever
but you would definitely be more like
you wouldn't be snacking you know
randomly like a lot of people do like
just I feel bored and I take something
from the fridge that that wouldn't be um
if you're practicing sense restraint or
or or seeing the danger in the sight is
fa you wouldn't be doing that but even
then for a monk like you know eating
eating one meal a day and stuff you
could still uh Overlook that right
motivation for eating because again the
defilements are beginningless it's not
that you need to consciously be
nurturing passion and Delight in your
mind for it to uh set in all you need to
do is have pleasant feeling and not have
the right context in regard to it and
lust is there
like it is immediately there so the same
the same applies with this like if if
you don't um you might even be
practicing sensal straint in terms of
not grasping the signs and features of
it but realistically speaking you still
end up eating more than you need um you
still end up um emphasizing you know
what food you prefer and and and other
stuff losing perspective of of the
actual uh purpose [Music]
[Music]
so when the biku eats in moderation the
realized one guides him further come
biku be committed to vigilance during
the day cleanse your mind of obstructive
States while walking or sitting during
the first watch of the night cleanse
your mind of obstructive States while
walking or sitting during the second
watch of the night you should lie down
in the liance posture on the right side
placing one foot on top of the other
recollected and aware having set the
intention to get up having gotten up in
the last watch of the night continue to
cleanse your mind of obstructive States
while walking or
sitting yeah
so obvious reason of course why that
would be after the moderation eating is
because some sutas would even talk about
how um there would be some monks who
would eat they would just big out during
the meal and then the immediate impulse
would be to go to sleep for the for the
right after the meal and then obviously
you wouldn't be able to do this like you
would just be
be lazy the whole day so that's why it
comes after the moderation eating and um
but then you that's already where the
the more kind of um so see your your
sense restraint you're definitely not planning
restraint you're definitely not planning
to break any of the
prps um
and uh that's already quite a quite a um
pure State compared to what you had
before it might not feel like it because
you know when you're there it never like
the dis pleasure that you have now
always feels like this is it you you
never have like perspective to compare
how it was in the past all you have is
what you have now so this will feel like
it's it's a lot but actually it's much
like just not necessarily do it but you can
just not necessarily do it but you can
know if I were to go back to Breaking
the precepts there would be a
significant difference in the amount of
uh wildness and and and the tameness
that that my mind exhibits so um
basically what I'm saying is that
already involves the degree of sadei
being in that state but you can go
further so obstructive States
um intentions like that's where you
would be starting to um look at these
more subtle things like you know you can
be having still worry still desires
still preoccupations um doubts about the
preoccupations um doubts about the
dummer about wholesome things quote
unquote um and that would that would
still be an obstructive state so you can
start looking at that so within this
restrained setup why what do I spend my
time thinking
about whether it's during the day during
the evening uh and after I wake up and
then that's the other thing
sleep um quite often like you go to
sleep and it's sort of like you give up
you kind of let go and then again you
don't necessarily need to want to enjoy
the sleep it's just automatic that uh as
other sisters would say you would be
indulging in the pleasure of lying down
and then the Buddha would say um yeah
you go to sleep but then as soon as you
as soon as you are awake you get up
because otherwise yeah automatically
that would be you indulging in that
pleasure sleep like you already woke up
but uh you choose to just
um just I'll just keep going the
there is a that kind of simple
instruction of noting the time for
waking right when you go to
bed it kind of nips this subtle tendency
right in the bud this tendency of just
you kind of just go to sleep and just
are hoping that it'll last forever yeah
in a way it's just like oh this is going
to be great you know you like you just
there's no kind of uh like foret
you're just like let's just yeah yeah
yeah it's but even then it's I wouldn't
necessarily translate it as noting the
time for waking up because that kind of
implies that you have a say sometimes
you might sleep for eight hours or more
because you factually tired it's more
like um having the the intention to wake up
um having the the intention to wake up
as it says uh so it's it's the the the
determination that you will wake up but
you will get up once you wake up M um so
because sometimes people could take that
in a wrong ways in predetermining the
amount of sleep that they will have as
often happens I think in meditation
meditation Retreats again uh like you're
you're expected to exactly wake up at
the same time and go to sleep at the
same time but right at the mathematical
like okay second watch of the night time
to fall asleep Third Watch of the night
all right I'm up right away but but
ideally yeah you want to recognize your
body has its own needs and uh you
your purpose should be that like the the
the light doesn't begin that the light
begins when you go beyond what the body
needs same with the food like it's it's
not necessarily lustful to eat but when
you eat beyond the the basic need of
survival and being able to practice
that's when it turns into something else
or would it be fair to say that that is
when it kind of is always going to be
Delight like you could just eat what you
need to survive but still be delighting
in it and sleeping just as much as you
need right that's when it's definitely
going to be roed in un wholesome
so so when the biku is committed to
vigilance the realized one guides him
further come biku be possessed of
recollection and awareness act with
awareness when going out and coming back
when looking a head and the side when
bending and extending the limbs when
bearing the outer robe bowl and robes
when eating drinking chewing and tasting
when urinating and defecating when
walking standing sitting sleeping
walking speaking and keeping silent
waking and keeping
silent yeah so that's where that comes
in now like um even within that within
that V vigilance that you have on a more
broader scope like U what am I spending
my time thinking about well you can
refine it even further like every little
movement you make now you have a a
clarity about the intention behind it
not like watching the sensation of my
elbow bending that's not that's not what
it means it's because you could be doing
that for um various un wholesome reasons
like uh again from the from the
perspective of somebody who was in the
beginning you would think oh that's
nothing that's harmless but for you now
that's the as as it would say um that
that I think it's a verse that would say
um just like a like a stain on a white
cloth like it stands out much more than
a stain on something that's almost
completely uh dirty so
um even these things you would be paying
attention now um at this point does
somebody even really kind of need
instruction if like the
most coarse ways that they're acting out
is in their like subtle
movements like kind of resisting like
kind of bodily displeasure well the
thing is uh the sutas would talk about
the noble aggregate of virtue even after
uh like this one doesn't mention it but
uh many of them would say even after the
virtue they would say endowed with the
sble aggregate of virtue so technically
even just keeping the
precepts uh should be should be enough
for someone to to get the right view but
up to in the end it's not up to you to
decide like you you just keep taking it
further if you see okay factually I
cannot see anything more to be done in
my virtue and yet I still don't have the
right view well then you go to the next
step and you don't you have you just uh
keep building it up until it's enough
for you to uh be withdrawn as as that
similarly of the wet sticks would say
like um you won't be able to light the fire
um you won't be able to light the fire
until the sticks are dry so you keep
going further in uh these these ways of
drying up the sticks and until
eventually it's dry enough for it to
light up so you you don't have a way to
predict how much is going to be
necessary but yeah so
um recollection and awareness as well uh
that's uh an aspect of the the noble AAL
path already so yeah technically by that
point ideally uh a person should have
the right View and then there's this
other sort of assembly of the cook that
says that if somebody doesn't see the
sign of the mind they won't be able to
have recollection and awareness so
that's when again you would end up
paying attention to these time tiny
things that are very secondary like your
Sensations and your knees and stuff but
really it's it's intentions of passion
aversion and distraction on the very
most subtle level that you would have to
to be aware of um like you know doing
bodily movements because you're
concerned about what other people think
about you or something which could I
mean could be on a on a on a whome level
like you know monks trying to be super
uh exaggerate almost the their
their um demeanor and their their their
conduct so as to gain appreciation and
and respect it could extend to to things
like that so every little thing you do
then you're aware why you're doing it
but see if you if you haven't been
developing these things and you start
with that even if you have the right
instruction that it should be about UNH
wholesome intentions and not about
watching Sensations in your body you
could still then become almost like uh
neurotic watching every every little
thing you do and you would be actually
overlooking in a way more fundamental
level like way from behind sensor
restraint you're you're basically taking
up these signs and features of these
thoughts and these these Notions that
you have and and grasping them which is
giving rise to to upset longing and
aversion so you're essentially
just like your reason
for trying
to like micromanage every movement and
whatnot at that point is actually
to kind of I guess it's kind of the
principle of sensuality still like you
are you're wanting to you're basically
wanting to get like some demeanor that
is satisfying and won't cause doubt yeah
it's a principle of well the whole thing
you could say it's
the a principle of management so the
gradual training is a gradual
abandonment of management management
meaning like trying to control what you
feel you could say in in the broadest
sense so precepts that's the very
obvious like you you don't do these
things regardless of how you feel so
that's that's already uh you giving up
quite a degree of control over what you
feel then sensor straint well why would
you be grasping these signs and features
because you hope even if it if it's not
explicitly that doing so will give rise
to more pleasure and uh prevent
displeasure and obviously ends up doing
the opposite so um then all the way to
this it would be uh yeah doing things
these little tiny things out of uh still
desire to control what you feel
feel and
um to that extent it's un wholesome even
if it's not immoral that's that's one of
the issue that you would confuse UNH
wholesomeness with immorality but it's
not the same like immorality was
abandoned long ago with the five
precepts actually immorality disappears
with the five precepts even the eight
precepts are actually not there's
nothing moral about sexual intercourse
there's there's nothing immoral about
entertainment there's nothing immoral
about eating the afternoon there's
nothing moral about sleeping in high and
luxurious beds now it's about yourself
and your from that point onwards it's
about yourself and your relationship
with your own mind what will make this
mind more
wild uh more passionate have more
craving and what will make it go in the
opposite
direction it could also like this
example of like monk or whoever like
he's in the the mon
or whatever set up and try to
micromanage his life in a way that every
single movement is kind of perfect but
like it doesn't even keep the preet Sens
strength and stuff actually lead him
lead him like quite in the like quite
away from what he's supposed to do
because it's like yeah again wanting to
like as you say like over manage
everything just because he's afraid of
like the pressure of doubt and these
kind of things like just doesn't
recognize situation I'm suffering I
don't even know why and I'm supposed to
follow that just trying to like over
manage everything and it's kind of yeah
and and and another aspect of that is uh
if you if you go into uh micromanagement
of these things again that's like it
says having
um
having felt touch with the body he
doesn't uh attend to the signs and
features that would give rise to longing
and upset so if you are attending into
your bodily Sensations more for the
purpose of giving rise to pleasure which
is what many people would conceive of as
meditation for example then your
grasping SS and features uh
so yeah that's why it's it goes on that
order that's interesting like in the
kind of like most of the Contemporary
setup is that we have in the west of
like Meditation Retreat and even like
Monastery and things like that like this
whole gradual training is like taken
totally the other way around like you
you are taught to sit down like watch
your mind not move like which is like
kind of this step and like you don't
have taken any precept yet like it's
kind of at the end of the week or at the
end of the 10 days or I don't know when
whatever or or you you might even assume
no as a result of the meditation I'll be
able to keep the precepts and what's
what is that really saying it's saying
you expect these things not to be
painful you want something that will
allow this to to to feel good but uh the
thing is when there is craving that's
being abandoned it cannot feel
good uh the the mind is is going to be
rebelling against that and then if it
doesn't feel at least some amount of not
necessarily like torture but some amount
of dissonance there that's probably
because you somehow
altered what you're actually see that's
where all these views would come in like
nothing is really real uh you know
things don't exist
so uh now you can let go of these things
and and yes start keeping the precepts
but because like you don't even
recognize like what those things are
now uh so so it's like
um it it's not the same thing anymore
you're not abandoning uh the same thing
anymore it's like you changed it into
something else and now you're abandoning
it so it's trying to kind
of make the dhama fit with my ignorance
you know like I'm ignorant so I don't
want it to be painful so I will like
kind of turn it around so I kind of and
and and that's not the the training the
the whole training
is each of these steps like when you're
fulfilling them none of them would
involve all of them would involve the
the the basic principle that we always
talk about endurance or patience in
regard to what is felt that is how you
would cultivate each of them so uh none
of them would involve
uh yeah managing feeling or trying to
control feeling you would end up doing
that if
you uh try to skip to something that
comes later but all of them would be
basically the same principle there is
this pleasure here or there is pleasure
here that I have a say in either giving
into and acting out of or
not so you're basically revealing these
layers of of Leaning leaning towards her
away from from pleasure and displeasure
when the biku is possessed of
recollection and awareness the realized
one guides him further come biku
frequent a secluded loding A wilderness
the root of a tree a hill a ravine a
mountain cave a chal ground a forest the
open air a heap of straw and he does so
after the meal he returns from alms
around sits down cross-legged sets his
body straight and establishes
recollection at the four giving up
longing with with in regard to the world
he abides with a mind of loving of
longing very different he cleanses the
mind of longing giving up aversion and
hatred he abides with the mind
of he abides with a mind rid of aversion
compassionate for the welfare of all
creatures and beings he cleanses the
mind of a virion and hatred giving up
indolence and lethargy he abides with a
mind rid of indolence and lethargy
perceiving light recollected and aware
he cleanses the mind of indolence and
lethargy giving up restlessness and
anxiety he abides without restlessness
his mind internally appeased he cleanses
the mind of restlessness and anxiety
giving up doubt he abides having gone
beyond doubt not uncertain about
beneficial qualities he cleanses the
mind of doubt he gives up these five
hindrances defilements of the mind that
weaken understanding then quite
destroyed from sensuality destroyed from
detrimental phenomena with thinking and
with pondering with joy and ease Bor
born of Separation he abides having
entered upon the first Jonah with the
appeasement of thinking and pondering
with internal confidence and and
collectiveness of mind without thinking
or pondering and with joy and ease born
of composure
composure um he abides having Enter he he abides
um he abides having Enter he he abides
having entered upon the second J with
the fading of Joy he abides equanimous
recollected and aware experiencing ease
with the body he abides having entered
upon the third third jna with regard to
which the noble ones say one abides
equanimous recollected and at ease with
the giving up of ease and unease with
the ending of happiness and sadness
beforehand without ease or unease with
purity of equinity and recollection he
abides having entered upon the fourth J
that's how I instruct the biku who are
trainees who haven't achieved their goal
but but live aspiring to the Supreme
safety from the Yoke but for those biku
who are arants who have destroyed the
influxes fulfilled the training done
what had to be done laid down the burden
arrived at the highest goal utterly
destroyed the feds of being and are
liberated through the right ultimate
knowledge these things lead to a
pleasant abiding within the present
experience and to a recollection and
awareness
yeah so that's now where this would come
in
um the the abandonment of longing and
and sensal desire all the all the
hindrances if you read other scps it
would say um I think it's sunaya 4651 it
would describe
that uh contrary to what you know our
natural inclination uh or natural assem
inclination uh or natural assem
assumtion the hindrances are not the
sign of beauty they're not the sign of
opposition or resistance or or dislike
you could say they're not uh tiredness
of mind even the sluggishness that
follows after a meal they're not uh
movements of of mind uh in the case of
restlessness and they're not the fact
that some things are
uncertain it's wrong attention
a attention not through the origin quote
unquote given to these things that
constitutes the hindrances
so if you started from this point your
view of what longing aversion and all
these things are would be whether you
realize it or not of
course oh these objects are the
hindrances and then naturally you would
use meditation for the wrong purpose of
basically not feeling things
anymore replacing one thing with the
other and uh that's where you would be
again by skipping all the all the
previous stages you would end up with
something else that's not
really the genre that that this or
describing because in fact there's
another one where specifically in the
cont context of the gradual training
that's majima
125 um when it would be describing that
point of samadi it would say it's like
an
elephant you took out of the woods which
is like the first step of of virtue you
take it out of the
woods um and then you gradually train it
to the point where even when it's being
attacked on all sides by you know men
with Spears and and bows and arrows and
and sounds of drums uh it doesn't quiver
it doesn't Flinch and it's it's fit to
be uh a royal elephant and uh that's
that's the Buddha describing the result
of practicing the force
atianas the first J and
so that shows
that all of the the the the stuff that
comes before is actually leading you to
that point where you'll be even more
able to endure things
not the opposite where you became so
delicate that now everything needs to be
like the way you want it including your
own thoughts um
thoughts um
so it's uh at that point then as it says
pleasure of or joy of separation of
being disjointed from these things means
like you your mind has become
so immovable that you have no need now
like you can generally allow them to be
to whatever degree they want to be
whereas before only thing you could do
was to either give into them or try to
get rid of them so all of this is well
actually that's another way you could
describe the gradual training it's the
gradual uh building up of the middle way
with the first step
virtue you don't uh as we've said before
you know you don't
um prevent their being things in the
world that you could
steal you don't uh stop speaking so that
you never tell a
lie uh you don't uh destroy the things
that could get you to break the precepts
you just prevent yourself from making
these intentions when these things are
there following that you have the signs
and features it doesn't say a monk
doesn't perceive signs and features when
he sees SES with the eye which sometimes
would be the Assumption like um again
with this whole underlying view that
things are not really real you would
think oh you see a site and then there's
like the bare perception of the site and
then there's like the the sort of
additional stuff stuff that you add to
it as if it's optional like what what
constitutes sites the arising of signs
and features but no it's not that it's
you don't grasp at the signs and
features even though they're there
next up uh eating again like I said you
don't prevent food from being Pleasant
you just don't eat it for the wrong
reason um sleepiness uh clearing your
mind from obstructive States and and
vigilance um you don't
uh yeah you don't prevent even the the
obstructive States from arising you
clear your mind from them so like um as
the sisters would say once once
um like how can you be
passionate how how can it be
passion if you're dispassionate in
regard to
it as it would say knowing a mind of
passion is mind of passion in
the he would abide with a mind
disengaged independent from anything in
the world so you
basically even now in that more
intimate or personal level uh you're
learning how to not get engaged or
involved with these things even while
they're there and uh same for the
recollection and and awareness like
that's already uh on that acute level of
samadi you wouldn't give in to uh even
the tiniest actions the state is in your
mind like the the pressure is there in
your mind you haven't gotten rid of it
but you're not allowing even these
tiniest actions to be motivated by it
which would result in reintroducing the
craving and finally the hindrances again
you don't prevent things from being
attractive or beautiful or Pleasant you
don't prevent them from being
disagreeable you don't prevent tiredness
from arising you don't prevent uh your
mind from moving here and there and you
don't prevent you don't try to find the
answer for everything so as to not have
doubt you just learn how to not be moved
by those things and that that is like
the the culmination or the real
um how to say like
the the core of the middle way like the
the most acute form of it would be that
and that's why actually the the suta
like that's the training that's it
there's nothing after that that is like
if you just stick to this eventually you
become an AR so
uh it doesn't talk about uh View and and
and purification of understanding
because these things would that would
come as a result of you clearing your
mind from these obstructions to
obviously to some extent you need to get
you know right instruction and um
replace wrong views with right views but
uh it won't become wisdom until you are
doing this which is clearing the Mind
from these these pollutions like the
Dust In Your Eyes is a call it clearing
the Dust In Your Eyes so that you would
see what's already there and um that's
the that's why always in the sance with
the for Jana like after the it says when
the mind is pliable purified rid of
obstructions then whichever way you
apply the
mind that thing that you're trying to
understand would become apparent whether
it's the recollection of past lives or
it's the uh understanding of K how
beings are reborn and stuff or the most
AC thing which is the four noble truths
uh you would be able to see it like the
Buddha would say it's like um when um
and you have a clear Pond I think we
mentioned that Sly last time like a
clear pond that's that's um like the mud
and stuff is not all over so you can
actually see what's inside then you
would see oh look these are the fish
swimming around and these are the
oysters and this is this and this is
that all of that understanding would
come as a result of the clear mind
uh that is built through that gradal
training so if a person doesn't have
that understanding uh that that's really
the one of the the
another way in which people would really
be wasting effort that they could uh
invest into into in a more productive
way like trying to directly create this
understanding of anata and Ana and and
really try to go into it and think that
the answer will come at the end of some
direct effort to to get it but really if
it's these things are there on their own
like you know form is already
impermanent it's feeling is already
impermanent perceptions are already
impermanent so you you just don't see it
because the mind hasn't been cleared of
obstructions through this so all of that
would just fit into place if you purify
your mind from the five hindrances it
would say it's like a like a river that
that's that's blocked by um I think it
says like logs and and debris and stuff
and the the flow of the river is blocked
but as soon as you remove it it would
just flow so it the same with it would
say it it's the same with the five
hindrances like people don't realize um
superhuman states don't realize higher
wisdom don't realize uh the nature of
things because of these five hindrances
and uh all of those like you can't
have uh be free from five hces on a
mental level while on a physical and
verbal level you still do the things
that are motivated by the five
hes it's it's said in fact that the five
hes are motiv are are nourished by
misconduct of body speech and mind
so again just to repeat that's why you
can't start there
if in fact if the connection
between uh like if if if it seems like I
can still abandon the five hindes but
sort of on the side keep doing these
things that's you could should take that
as a sign that at least according to the
Buddhist definition that what you
abandoning there is not the
five it was like one of the kind of
common view like that contemporary
teacher can teach often it's like the
historical Dimension and then the
ultimate Dimension so like you know like
these two like kind of separate reals
that are or conventional reality and
ultimate yeah yeah exactly like that are
don't have connection so like I think
it's one of the things is that yeah I'm
doing my two hours contemplation of
whatever like Ana in the morning so then
in the day I can go have a drink with my
friend and engage in whatever things
because in the evening I know I sit down
again and I contate that again so I'm
making progress toward understanding but
actually not at all and you would even
think sometimes that's how warped it
gets like you would think oh but you're
not supposed to be attached so why are
you getting attached to the to the
precept and stuff yes you you do have to
abandon it it says s bamasa and and uh
all these um ultimately even craving for
the dama you would
abandon but not before fulfilling these
things like it would come as a result of
all all this this understanding would
come as a result of of these things so
that's why they would say the Dum is
like a raft like you're you can't drop
the raft before you have actually uh
gone any distance with it so if you want
to clean a house this is something I've
thought about cuz people like ah like
you know isn't wanting to free yourself
from suffering craving it's like if you
want to clean a house like remove
everything and make it spotless first
step is certainly not to remove the
cleaning supplies like
yeah
yeah yeah and and uh I think there's
another there's a simile he gave there
would be
quite useful to read
read
so the Brahman essentially asks why do
some people get it and some people
don't and some people even though they
in the Buddha instructs even though
they're given this instruction from the
Buddha himself so he says what do you
think Brahman suppose a person was to
come along who wanted to go to rajagaha
he'd approach you and say sir I wish to
go to rajagaha please point out the road
to rajagaha oh I I ski the point the
Buddha asks if he is familiar with the
way to rajagaha which he is so then you
would say to them here Mis this road
goes to rajagaha go along it for a while
you'll see a certain Village go along a
while further you'll see a certain Town
go along a while further and you'll see
rajagaha with its delightful Parks Woods
Meadows and Lotus ponds instructed like
this by you they might still take the
wrong road heading west but a second
person might come with the same question
receive the same instructions instructed
by you they might safely arrive at
rajagaha what is the cause Brahman what
is the reason why though rajagaha is
present the path leading to rajagaha is
present and you are there to encourage
them one person takes the wrong path and
heads West while another arrives safely
at rajagaha what can I do about that
Master Guma I am I'm the one who shows
the way in the same way though nibana is
available the path leading to nabana is
available and I am present to encourage
them still some of my disciples
instructed and advised like this achieve
the ultimate goal nibana while some of
them fail what can I do about that
Brahman the realized one is the one who
shows the
way yeah so it's um if you're given
directions to go somewhere and you were
supposed to turn left like after having
turned left right left right 10 times
but you start with that what's that
going to result you won't end up from
the place you were supposed to be in so
the same applies with this if you try to
do any of these steps um before the
others you try to shift the order or
something you won't end up
in the right uh place that the Buddha
was was uh intending you to end up with
you might end up with something that
pleases you and feels good but that
doesn't mean that that's what the Buddha
wanted you to get to right so there's a
um just in kind of my rock climbing
background um near where I lived for a
while there's a big cliff and there's a
roote on it called Sam Swan Song and
it's a relatively easy route in terms of
like it's not physically difficult
but the um like if you're an experienced
climber you're used to kind of looking
for certain like cracks and features in
the Rock and essentially what makes this
so difficult is that
if you go based on that in Instinct you
will be deceived into some pretty
horrendous situations so you need like
very specific instructions for how to
get up this thing and every
single bit of it is essentially having
you go against your gut instinct as a
climber so CU that could be a similar
analogy yeah because the the whole
instinct is like if if you didn't have
the instruction from the Buddha there's
like very little chance and you might
cultivate like as it would say um in the
past athetics and Brahman would would
keep the
precepts um but yeah it would be enough
for them to to end up in heaven and
stuff but even to get to the point of
samadi like it would be very few that
would find out how to do that on their
own so yeah your instinct will almost
always lead you to the to the wrong
direction and yeah the thing is like
um it's not that uh as I mentioned
before it's not that there's
some Magical Force that's stopping you
uh from getting to the goal it's it's
really the fact
that if you already knew even what
you're supposed to do you would already
be there so it's not like I already know
what I'm supposed to do but still
somehow like the four fourth Noble Truth
is the knowledge of the path to niana
and it says that whoever sees the Four
Noble Truth sees all the others so if
you know how to get there you already
got there that's a that's that's the
whole thing so um that's why the the
instruction of another is essential it's
not that you can like I do know how to
get there but I haven't really that's
that that's
not even even for a noble disciple like
he might have a general idea of what the
arship is but the fact that he doesn't
have it yet means he he's not clear
enough about how he should go about
developing it he knows the outlines the
blueprint to to build a house but uh
he's not
necessarily uh sure about why you know I
put this here but it's still kind of
wobbly and it doesn't really seem like
it fit eventually he'll figure it out
inevitably at least within seven
lifetimes but fundamentally if you know
exactly how to build the
house every single step of the way it's
because you already built the
house so that's why you can never uh put
aside the the need for for external
instruction and you can never think like
like oh I already figured it out or
something that's only interesting that
uh also that
the the Buddha like in like when you sh
the simil it doesn't just say oh yeah
like the road is there carry along and
you will get there you say like actually
like again as a gradual things like
first you will meet a village don't stop
there there will be a t don't stop there
and then you will get there so it's kind
of like interesting as well yeah cuz
sometimes you will be told oh just just
as long as you're following what is
wholesome you would just get there as if
you already know what is wholesome from
the St that was in the very last thing
is putting aside doubt about what is
like there's no kind of longer any
questioning about what is and isn't
wholesome not by finding answers but by
realizing oh what's wholesome is not to
resist the discomfort and not knowing
the answer and that's the answer to everything for